טוב. tov. Today's דף daf is ל"ה. lamed hey. We pick up
in the middle of ל"ד עמוד ב' lamed daled amud bais
and we are dealing with the debate in the משנה mishnah between
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, how to read
the פסוקים psukim in the תורה Torah that says you split the
live animal and the dead animal
where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir reads it that the dead animal is
worth nothing, it doesn't really mean you split the dead animal, it
really means you split the depreciation due to death, and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says no you split the live and the dead one.
Now this only works out if the animals were of equal value,
as the גמרא Gemara has begun to illustrate. And the גמרא Gemara
says that the point of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that the מזיק
mazik is a part owner in the carcass, you would think it
means that he could also suffer the loss if the value of
the carcass goes down, but that would make תם tam more severe
than other types of מועד muad and other types of נזק nezek
because other types of נזק nezek it's the ניזק nizak that fully
owns the carcass. So why here should the מזיק mazik be a
part owner and suffer in the loss? So it actually winds up
that according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the מזיק mazik is a
part owner only for the purpose of if the value of the
carcass goes up, then he benefits in the appreciation of the value.
So that's the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads the פסוק pasuk more literally
and has the מזיק mazik as a part owner in the carcass
at least for purposes of appreciation. But now the גמרא Gemara continues
on the top of ל"ד עמוד ב' lamed daled amud bais and
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, ella
amar Rabbi Yochanan, line about 12 lines down, something like 12 lines
down. Okay, אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, ella amar Rabbi Yochanan, so says
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, שבח נבילה איכא בינייהו. shvach niveila ika beinaihu.
The difference of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is if the carcass increases in value. Certainly if it decreases in
value the ניזק nizak suffers that, that would be true in the
case of a מועד muad so it's certainly true in the case
of a תם. tam. But if the carcass increases in value, then
the מזיק mazik as a part owner at least he gains in
some of that increase in value. שבח נבילה איכא בינייהו. shvach niveila
ika beinaihu. דמר סבר דניזק הוי, de-mar savar denizak havei,
one holds even that's of the ניזק, nizak, like in other cases,
that would be רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ומר סבר umar savar and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds no, פלגא, palga, that half of the
appreciation goes to the מזיק mazik and that's the fulfillment of the
verse that they split the carcass. היינו דקקשיא ליה לרבי יהודה. hainu
de-ka kasha lei le-Rabbi Yehuda. That's what was bothering רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda in the following ברייתא. braisa. Since רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has
the reality that the case of תם, tam, not only do you
pay half, but you even get this extra benefit, the מזיק, mazik,
that you gain in the appreciation of the carcass, so he raised
the following logical problem. השתא דאמרת חס רחמנא עלויה דמזיק, hashta demarta
chas Rachmana ilvei de-mazik, now that you say that the תורה Torah
actually has compassion on the מזיק, mazik, goes easy on him, lets
him gain in the appreciation of the carcass, דשקיל בשבחה, deshakil bishvacha,
that he takes some of the appreciation of the carcass, so if
that's true let's imagine the following case. שור שוה חמש סלעים שנגח
שור שוה מנה. shore shaveh chamesh sela'im shenagach shore shaveh maneh.
Let's say an ox worth twenty gored an ox worth a hundred.
Now the case of the תורה, Torah, right, or the only way
in which the תורה's Torah case makes sense that it's fair is
assuming that the animals are worth the same amount. So when you
split the live one and you split the carcass of the dead
one you wind up paying for half the damages. But let's say
the actual values were different. Let's say it's a case of שור
שוה חמש סלעים שנגח שור שוה מנה. shore shaveh chamesh sela'im shenagach
shore shaveh maneh.
Let's say the goring ox was twenty and the gored ox was
a hundred. Okay, here we'll make big horns here so you see
it's the one that's goring. Okay, okay. והנבילה יפה חמשים זוז. vehaniveila
yafeh chamishim zuz.
And now this goes down to fifty. Okay,
so the actual damage was fifty. You should pay half, twenty-five, which
basically means the whole ox should go over to the ניזק. nizak.
But let's say you do the פסוק pasuk as it's literally written:
זה נוטל חצי חי וחצי מת וזה נוטל חצי חי וחצי מת.
zeh notel chatzi chai vechatzi meis vezeh notel chatzi chai vechatzi meis.
If you do the פסוק pasuk like it's written, so they split
this, they split the live one, each one takes ten dollars from
the live one, and they split the dead one, each one takes
twenty-five dollars from the dead one. So the מזיק mazik walks away
with thirty-five dollars. Half of his live one and half of the
guy's dead one. He walks away with thirty-five dollars. His ox to
begin with was only twenty dollars. He gains from it, right? So
this is why the תורה Torah had to be talking that the
oxen are worth the same. Because if this ox is worth, if
this ox is worth a lot more then the ניזק nizak will
gain more than the damage done. If this ox is worth a
lot more then the מזיק mazik will walk away with a profit.
Okay. היכן מצינו מזיק נשכר? heichan matzinu mazik niskar?
But how could that be? How could the מזיק mazik walk away
with a profit? שזה נשכר, she-zeh niskar, that this one should walk
away with a profit, when did we ever find such a thing?
ואומר ve-omer and the verse says שלם ישלם, shalem yeshalem, pay. בעלי
משלמין. ba'alei meshalamin.
The owner of the goring ox pays ואין בעלי נוטלין. ve-ein ba'alei
notlin. The owner of the goring ox doesn't walk away with a
profit, doesn't take something. So he is the one that pays out
of pocket. Okay, מאי ואומר mai v'omer now why do now so
and the point is what underscores the bizarre now because you know
the הוה אמינא hava amina meaning the גמרא Gemara is saying what's
the הוה אמינא? hava amina? Well, since we find says רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda that the מזיק mazik actually does get part ownership of
the carcass and does get the increased value of the carcass that
the תורה Torah is going easy on the מזיק, mazik, if the
תורה Torah is going easy on the מזיק mazik maybe it'll allow
the מזיק mazik to even walk away with a profit in a
scenario like this? No, that's too absurd. It's one thing to say
that he gains from the appreciation of the carcass. It's another thing
to say that the תורה Torah will let him walk away with
an actual profit out of the whole thing. Okay, now מאי ואומר
mai v'omer why did you need to say a second פסוק pasuk
meaning why it's why isn't it just enough to say that you
know it's illogical that the מזיק mazik should get a profit? Why
do you have to quote a פסוק pasuk that says the מזיק
mazik pays and the מזיק mazik doesn't take? מאי ואומר, mai v'omer,
וכי תימא v'chi teima הני מילי היכא דאיכא פסידא לניזק. hani mili
heicha d'ika pseida l'nizak.
That's true in this case that it clearly would be unfair that
the מזיק mazik would walk away with a profit and the ניזק
nizak would be obviously out money, right? He'd be left with thirty-five
dollars from an ox that was worth a hundred and he'd be
walking away with a profit. That you don't need a פסוק pasuk
to tell you you don't do that. That's clearly unfair. אלא היכא
דליכא פסידא לניזק. Ela heicha d'leika pseida l'nizak. Let's say there would
not be a loss to the ניזק. nizak. What would be the
scenario? כגון שור שוה חמש סלעים שנגח שור שוה חמש סלעים. k'gon
shor shaveh chamesh s'la'im shenagach shor shaveh chamesh s'la'im. Let's say each
of them was worth twenty. Okay, okay, ונבילה יפה שלשים
זוז.
v'neveila yafeh shloshim
zuz.
But let's say ironically after this ox was gored and it now
is dead, okay, there's been a appreciation of the values, I'm trying
to make it look less like a person but I don't know
if I'm succeeding, anyway let's say there's been appreciation of the values
of dead oxen, okay, the market's gone up and even now that
it's dead it's worth thirty. Okay, so if you split, okay, you've
got ten and ten and fifteen and fifteen, okay, so if you
split, מזיק mazik walks away with twenty-five a profit but the ניזק
nizak also walks away with twenty-five, so he also gets a profit,
everybody wins! Okay, now obviously the ניזק nizak doesn't really win because
if his ox hadn't been gored it would have been worth even
more, but at least he's not out money from prior to what
happened prior to the actual act of damage. So maybe in a
case where the מזיק mazik walks away with a profit and the
ניזק nizak doesn't even lose money, maybe at least this case you
should say let's everybody split let's split everything. Okay, so אלא היכא
דליכא פסידא לניזק כגון שור שוה חמש סלעים שנגח שור שוה חמש
סלעים ונבילה יפה שלשים זוז שקיל מזיק ממש
פלגא. ela heicha d'leika pseida l'nizak k'gon shor shaveh chamesh s'la'im shenagach
shor shaveh chamesh s'la'im v'neveila yafeh shloshim zuz shakil mazik mamish palga.
Since the תורה Torah anyway says according says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
since I'm telling you that the תורה Torah lets the מזיק mazik
own part of the נבילה, neveila, maybe the מזיק mazik would be
entitled to own part of the נבילה neveila even if it would
mean he would walk away with a profit. Meaning not just own
the נבילה neveila to offset his loss as the value of the
נבילה neveila goes up, but maybe he's so much a part owner
of the נבילה neveila that it can even offset his profit. Okay,
ואומר v'omer
so therefore it says
ואומר v'omer the verse says שלם ישלם בעלים משלמים ואין בעלים נוטלים.
shalem yeshallem ba'alim meshalmim v'ein ba'alim notlim. No,
I'm sorry, his ownership of the נבילה neveila is enough to offset
loss but not enough to gain a profit. Okay, by the way,
maybe a more reasonable scenario would be let's say when the damage
was done originally the נבילה neveila went down to ten dollars, okay,
and they each owned five. But now the market's gone up and
over time this five dollars is now worth fifteen, right? So let's
say that well since you told me that the תורה Torah says
that the מזיק mazik gets half the נבילה neveila and the מזיק
mazik gets the increase in value of the נבילה, neveila, maybe even
if the נבילה neveila increases so much that lets the מזיק mazik
walk away with a profit, because you told me the מזיק mazik
gets the appreciation of the נבילה, neveila, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says no, there's a limit. He gains the appreciation of the נבילה
neveila to offset his payment, but he cannot gain so much that
he can actually walk away with a profit out of this whole
thing. Okay, so that's what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is saying. Yes,
the תורה Torah goes easy on the מזיק, mazik, it lets him
own part in the נבילה neveila in order that he gains from
the appreciation, but that's only if the appreciation offsets his payment, not
to the point that he would actually walk away with a profit.
Yes, Dov.
Let's first just put Dov on this thing and then we'll go
to questions.
Most cultures wouldn't have Dov on this thing.
Well it depends which religion you are. Okay, yes Dov.
Is the תורה's Torah's issue it's one of רחמים rachamim or is
it like a גניבה, gneiva, like in other words I gored your
ox so I have my hand in it in a way?
Oh you're sort of like you break it you buy it type
of a thing? That's an interesting perspective on it, like you break
it you buy it and you pay for the loss.
There's a שינוי shinuy that's been stolen you've got a hand in
it.
Yeah, I suppose, but that would be a principle that you would
pay for the entire as if the thing was worth zero and
then you should take full ownership of it, but I hear your
logic. Like if you're... splitting everything.
I guess I'm asking is that in play here or just a
matter of, no, you're right.
That's a good point. It's a good way of thinking about it
because it is true that maybe the splitting is sort of saying
like it's like I guess yeah it's interesting. It relates it gets
to the general question though that by מועד muad then you should
say you pay the full value and you fully own the carcass,
but we don't say that, right? It only works halfway you only
gain that's what the גמרא'ס Gemara's point is according to this you're
only gaining if the carcass goes up, not if the carcass goes
down. All right, so, but I hear the point. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
So if the carcass goes up then the one who was damaged
might have increased profit only because rather than getting half he's getting
more than half?
No, if
it goes according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, if it goes up
normally the one who was damaged would get all the profit. But
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the מזיק mazik the תורה Torah
goes easy on the מזיק mazik and lets the מזיק mazik gain
half of the appreciation but not to the point that he can
walk away with the profit. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר ליה רב אחא בר תחליפא לרבא אם כן מצינו לרבי
יהודה תם משלם יותר מחצי נזק והתורה אמרה ומכרו
את השור החי וחצו את כספו. Amar lei Rav Acha bar Tachlifa
le-Rava: Im kein matzinu le-Rabbi Yehuda tam meshalem yoter me-chatzi nezek ve-ha-Torah
amra: ve-machru et ha-shor ha-chai ve-chatzu et kaspo. So he says like
this: he says one minute
according to this that
one minute wait let me just check רש"י. Rashi.
Hold on.
Right. So רש"י Rashi says let's say he says look if רבי
יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's going to be such a literal reading of the
פסוק, pasuk, let's take the following scenario. Let's say there was a
case of 50 that gored an ox worth 40, okay?
And let me just check one minute.
Okay. Okay. And then it went down to 20, okay? So what
would be what would we say in this case, right? We would
say in this case okay split this 25-25,
split this 10-10, and everybody walks away with 35, right? Okay. Everyone
walks away with 35. So in this case the מזיק mazik doesn't
walk away with a profit. He only walks away with 35. The
ניזק nizak doesn't walk away with more than his ox was worth,
he also only walks away with 35, right? Everybody with me here?
Yes, you see that? Everybody walks away with 35 in this case.
But there's a problem because even though he doesn't walk away with
the profit and he doesn't walk away with the profit, the מזיק
mazik is paying more than half. He's paying 35, right? You with
me here? So the problem is the גמרא Gemara before ruled out
for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the scenario of like 100 and 20.
That would be impossible then the ניזק nizak would walk away with
a profit, right? It ruled out a scenario of the reverse of
20 and 100. That would be impossible that way the מזיק mazik
would walk away I mean that way the מזיק mazik would walk
away with a profit. But רבא Rava says but you can get
a middle case where there's a gap not a huge gap and
nobody walks away with a profit but if you read the פסוקים
pesukim literally okay split and split the ניזק nizak walks away with
more than half. How should that be that the ניזק nizak could
walk away with more than half? Okay that's his question. אמר ליה
רב אחא בר תחליפא לרבא אם כן מצינו לרבי יהודה תם משלם
יותר מחצי נזק והתורה אמרה ומכרו את השור החי וחצו את כספו.
Amar lei Rav Acha bar Tachlifa le-Rava: Im kein matzinu le-Rabbi Yehuda
tam meshalem yoter me-chatzi nezek ve-ha-Torah amra: ve-machru et ha-shor ha-chai ve-chatzu
et kaspo. So you just split it which presumably would mean like
you're never going to pay more than half. I mean רבי יהודה'ס
Rabbi Yehuda's whole emphasis had been to go easier on the מזיק.
mazik. But he's also a more literal reader of the פסוקים. pesukim.
So we've excluded extreme cases where the מזיק mazik has a profit
or the ניזק nizak has a profit. But if you have a
middle case like 50 and 40 you'll have paying more than half.
How is that possible? So the גמרא Gemara says no. אית ליה
לרבי יהודה פחת שפחתה מיתה מחצין בחי. is lei le-Rabbi Yehuda pachat
she-pachtah mitah machatzin be-chai. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually also agrees: in
the end of the day the מזיק mazik is only going to
pay half of the depreciation of how much it went from being
alive to being dead. מנא ליה? mena lei? Where does he learn
that from? וגם את המת יחצון. ve-gam et ha-meit ye-chetzun. That it
says you split the dead animal which to him means you split
the depreciation due to death. ואזדו רבי יהודה לזה נוטל חצי חי
וחצי המת וזה נוטל חצי חי וחצי
המת? ve-azdu Rabbi Yehuda le-zeh noteil chatzi chai ve-chatzi ha-meit ve-zeh noteil
chatzi chai ve-chatzi ha-meit? But one minute, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
you learn from that פסוק pasuk a more literal read: each one
gets half of the live one, half of the dead one. Not
the fundamental idea that you only get half, you only pay half
the depreciation.
No. אי הכי לכתוב קרא ואת המת. ei hachi lichtov kra ve-et
ha-meit. Then let it just say split the live, split the dead.
מאי וגם? mai ve-gam? Also split the dead? שמע מינה תרתי. shma
mina tarti. So the פסוק pasuk is telling you two things. Number
one it's telling you a literal idea you split the live, you
split the dead for a case when they are both worth the
same. In a case where they're both worth the same right if
they were both worth the same what would you have here? You'd
have this 35. 35, if it had gone down 30, he would
have paid 15. If they're both worth the same you do the
math and what winds up in a case where they're both worth
the same? Let's do an easier case, right, if you had a
100 and a 100, right, then what would happen if they were
both worth the same? If they were both worth the same, he'd
walk away, each one would walk away with $60, right, which would
be half a which would be meaning pay 40 which is half
of the loss, right? Everybody see this? Goes down from 100 to
20 to an $80
loss, each one walks away with 60, so they split the loss,
each one paid lost $40. So רב יהודה Reb Yehuda holds in
the the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim tells you you own
half the נבילה neveilah so you gain in the in the appreciation
of the נבילה. neveilah. That's what we've been saying. But it also
the פסוקים psukim should only be read when both animals are worth
the same, because if the animals are worth different amounts, it's either
going to lead to paying less than half or more than half
or walking away with a profit or walking away the other guy
you a one guy walking away with a profit, okay, or paying
less or a different amount than half. So you have to read
the פסוקים psukim that they're worth the same. And the חידוש chidush
is that you get half of the נבילה. neveilah. But if they're
worth different amounts, right, if this is worth whatever, I'm not going
to do the math again, but if they're worth different amounts, then
the payment will be different than a half. How does he know
that the payment is a half? The פסוק pasuk וגם את המת
יחצו v'gam es hameis yechetzu tells you two things. Partly it tells
you המת יחצו hameis yechetzu that they split the נבילה neveilah and
you gain in the appreciation of the נבילה, neveilah, but the וגם
v'gam tells you that you basically split pay for
half of the total depreciation, that he's not debating the basic principle
that the amount that's going to be paid is half of the
depreciation. Okay, so when the animals are worth different amounts, you figure
out the depreciation due to death and then the other guy gets
half of the ownership of the cow based on that. Alright, so
there really are at the bottom at the end of the day,
nobody treats the פסוקים psukim literally in all scenarios. You read the
פסוקים psukim literally in all scenarios, you wind up paying widely different
amounts and you could get that the ניזק nezek walks away with
a profit, the מזיק mazik walks away with a profit, you pay
a different amount than half, it's crazy. Everybody reads it that you
only basically pay half of the loss due to death and that
the ניזק nezek gets ownership of the cow or a lien on
the cow based on half damages. Everybody agrees to that. The only
bottom line difference is that according to רב יהודה, Reb Yehuda, the
מזיק mazik gets a part ownership in the carcass so that if
it appreciates that offsets the amount of payment that he has to
make. Alright, everybody pretty clear on that? More or less? As clear
as you're going to get. Okay, it's as clear as mud. We're
moving on.
The ניזק nezek keeps the literal carcass?
The ניזק... nezek... Well, it's not clear according to רב יהודה Reb
Yehuda whether the מזיק mazik really owns half... It's funny that you
could be a real owner but only it would only affect you
if it moved up in moved in one direction rather than the
other. So the way I would read it according to רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda is that the ניזק nezek owns the carcass but if
the carcass increases in value it offsets the payment that the מזיק
mazik has to make. Right, because the גמרא Gemorah also says if
it goes up you wouldn't get a profit out of it going
up it would just offset your payment. Okay, so at the end
of the day the פסוקים psukim are talking about the animals are
worth the same amount, everybody agrees that you pay half damages, and
the whole debate is that according to רב יהודה Reb Yehuda if
the carcass goes up in value it offsets the payment that the
מזיק mazik makes. Alright, let's move on. Okay, יש חייב yesh chayav
now we get to a different topic. I mean, we're still with
שור shor but a little bit a little of a little bit
different nature. יש חייב על מעשה שורו ופטור על מעשה עצמו פטור
על מעשה שורו וחייב על מעשה עצמו. yesh chayav al ma'aseh shoro
upatur al ma'aseh atzmo patur al ma'aseh shoro v'chayav al ma'aseh atzmo.
There's some type of an ox that if your ox did it
you'd pay but if you did it you'd be exempt. Or the
reverse, if you did it you'd pay but if your ox did
it you'd be exempt. כיצד, keitzad, what's the case? שורו שביייש, shoro
she'bi'eish, if your ox embarrasses somebody, פטור, patur, then you're exempt because
you only pay for בושת boshes the same way you only pay
for צער tza'ar and ריפוי ripuy and שבת, sheves, all those additional
payments for personal injury, those are only by case where a human
being inflicts personal injury, not when their animal inflicts injury. If my
animal gores somebody, I don't pay hospital bills, I don't pay pain
and suffering, I only pay damages. So similarly for embarrassment. If my
ox embarrasses somebody you don't pay. והוא שביייש חייב, v'hu she'bi'eish chayav,
but if you embarrass somebody then you do pay. שורו שסימא את
עין עבדו והפיל את שינו, shoro she'sima es ein avdo v'hipil es
shino, here's another case. The ox gores out the eye or the
tooth of the of a slave. פטור, patur, you're exempt because when
the Torah says if you knock out the eye or tooth of
your slave your slave goes free, that's only when you personally do
it, not when your animal does it. והוא שסימא את עין עבדו
והפיל את שינו חייב, v'hu she'sima es ein avdo v'hipil es shino
chayav, you're obligated or meaning then the slave goes free. שורו שחבל
באביו ואמו... shoro she'chaval b'aviv v'imo... that's cases where your ox is
חייב chayav and you are פטור. patur.
Why'd you bring the second case first?
I have no idea. שור... שורו... שורו... שורו וקדשי קנס. shoro v'kadshei
k'nas. שורו שחבל באביו ואמו חייב. shoro she'chaval b'aviv v'imo chayav. Oh,
you mean why in the... I don't know. It's an ABBA, a
chiastic structure. שור שחבל באביו ובאמו חייב. Shor shechaval b'aviv u'v'imo chayav.
If your ox gores your father or mother, then you would pay
your father or mother for the damages. והוא שחבל באביו ובאמו, V'hu
shechaval b'aviv u'v'imo, but if you injure, do physical injury to your
father or mother, and חבלה chavala means it's a type of a
wound where so in that case פטור patur you're exempt because you're
חייב מיתה chayav misa because if a person wounds a parent, then
that's a punishment deserving of death, so there will be no payment.
So that's a case where your ox is liable and you're exempt.
Similarly, שור שהדליק את הגדיש בשבת חייב. Shor shehidlik et hagedish b'shabbat
chayav. If your ox lights a, takes a torch and lights a
pile of grain on Shabbat, you're חייב. chayav. Okay, that would be
whether it be צרורות tzroros or whatever it would be. We had
that whole case with the dog and the fire, but there would
be some payment. והוא שהדליק את הגדיש בשבת פטור, V'hu shehidlik et
hagedish b'shabbat patur, but if you did it, you'd be exempt because
you were מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat, so we'd say קמליה, kimlei, which
we'll talk about that in the גמרא, Gemara,
מפני שמתחייב בנפשו. mipnei shemitchayev b'nafsho. In those last two cases, the
reason you're exempt is because you've done a sin deserving of death
and therefore that overrides any payment you might make. So let's take
a look at this idea, קמליה. kimlei. There's like a whole פרק
perek in כתובות Ketubot that focuses on קמליה. kimlei. Here we have
it for one little passage of the גמרא. Gemara. תני רבי אבהו
קמיה דרבי יוחנן. Tani Rabbi Abbahu kammai d'Rabbi Yochanan. Rabbi Abbahu taught
in the presence of Rabbi Yochanan. כל המקלקלים פטורים חוץ מחובל ומבעיר.
Kol hamikalkelim paturim chutz mechovel u'mav'ir. All types of times you do
a מלאכה melacha on Shabbat, but the effect of the מלאכה
melacha
is to be destructive, okay, let's say one מלאכה melacha is, I
don't know, is erasing, but let's say you had a Shakespeare manuscript
and you erased it. That would be an example of מקלקל. mikalkel.
So let's say if you do a מלאכה melacha on Shabbat, but
ultimately it's destructive, you are פטור patur with the exception of wounding
and making a fire. Okay, now because the גמרא Gemara learns it
out from פסוקים pesukim in a different גמרא, Gemara, but you could
also understand that those acts are acts that sort of the paradigmatic
version of those acts often have a very destructive component, right? Now
one version of wounding is שחיטה shechting an animal because you're wounding
it, but ultimately you're turning it into meat. Making a fire can
be very productive. You could be creating heat or cooking something, but
there's also something fundamentally destructive about those acts and therefore he says
that those acts, even if they were fully destructive, that's still a
מלאכה melacha on Shabbat and you're חייב. chayav. So this is what
Rabbi Abbahu taught in front of Rabbi Yochanan, a ברייתא. braita. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, Rabbi Yochanan said to him, פוק תני לברא, puk
tani l'bara, go teach that outside. Like he rejected that ברייתא. braita.
That's not a correct
ברייתא. braita. Forget, don't teach it in the בית מדרש. beis medrash.
חובל ומבעיר אינו משנה. Chovel u'mav'ir eino mishnah. This, it's not a
משנה. mishnah. This teaching that you're חייב chayav for מקלקל mikalkel by
those things is false.
You're always פטור patur for everything, even מקלקל, mikalkel, even for those.
ואם תמצא לומר משנה, V'im timtza lomar mishnah, and if you say
that it is a legitimate teaching, a legitimate ברייתא, braita, it's only
in the following case. חובל וצריך לכלבו, Chovel v'tzarich l'kabboy, not when
you're a total מקלקל. mikalkel. There needs to be an element of
תיקון. tikun. If you are wounding because you want some type of
a thing, a person, an animal, and you want to get the
blood out, but the reason you want to get the blood out
is because you want to give your dog some blood. Okay, or
מבעיר וצריך לאפרו, mav'ir v'tzarich l'afro, or you're burning down a nice,
beautiful table, but you want to use the ashes. Okay, so meaning
in the macro it's destructive. You ruined a nice thousand-dollar table. But
it's not totally destructive. You had some constructive purpose from it. You
wanted to use those ashes to do something with those ashes. You
wounded your cow and made a hundred dollars' worth of damage, but
you got some blood out of it to feed to your dog.
Okay, so basically I will concede that maybe you're חייב chayav for
מקלקל, mikalkel, but you need an element of תיקון. tikun. If it's
fully מקלקל, mikalkel, you would be פטור. patur. All right, so that's
the debate. תנן, Tnan, let's take a look at our משנה. mishnah.
שור שהדליק את הגדיש בשבת חייב. Shor shehidlik et hagedish b'shabbat chayav.
An ox lights a pile of grain, you're liable. והוא שהדליק את
הגדיש בשבת פטור. V'hu shehidlik et hagedish b'shabbat patur. But if a
person did it, you're exempt because it's a חילול שבת. chilul Shabbat.
וקתני, V'katani, הוא hu דומיא דשורו. dumya d'shoro. It sounds like the
act the person did is in a similar scenario as the act
that the ox did. So מה שור דלא קבעי ליה, ma shor
d'lo kaba'i lei, the same way when an ox lights a גדיש,
gadish, lights a barrel of grain, it is not interested in the
ashes, right? It's only doing it as a purely destructive act. Either
as a mindless act or as a destructive act, but it's certainly
not doing it because it wants to benefit from the ash. אף
הוא נמי דלא קבעי ליה. Af hu nami d'lo kaba'i lei. So
when you do it, presumably you're not interested in the ashes. It's
a purely destructive act and nevertheless you see it's considered חילול שבת.
chilul Shabbat. So you see that making a fire, even if it's
purely destructive, is considered חילול שבת. chilul Shabbat. That's the case by
the ox, presumably that's the case by you. וקתני פטור, V'katani patur,
you're exempt, מפני שנידון בנפשו, mipnei shenidon b'nafsho, so because you're liable
for a capital crime. So you see that you're liable, it's חילול
שבת Chilul Shabbos even if you don't need the ashes. So גמרא
Gemara says לא, lo, no, not necessarily. שור דומיא דידיה. Shor dumya
dideh. No, we'll actually say the opposite, that the ox is like
the case of you. We don't presume the ox isn't intentional or
isn't trying to get benefit. We'll assume that a human being doesn't
act because he wants to get benefit. And that's same as the
case of the ox. So מהו דקבליה, Mahu d'kabaleh, the same way
if you burned down this pile of grain, presumably you had some
benefit to gain from it, you wanted to use the ashes. אף
שור דקבליה, Af shor d'kabaleh, so when the ox did it we
would also be talking about a case that the ox wanted to
get some benefit. Why would what benefit would the ox want to
get? So שור היכי משכחת לה, Shor heichi mishkachas lo, what would
be the case? אמר ליה רב אחא הכא במאי עסקינן, Amar leh
Rav Achai hacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about? בשור פיקח,
Beshor pikeach, a very smart ox. שעשה לו נשיכה בגבו, She'asa lo
neshicha begabo, it got a bite on its back. Okay. וקבעי למיקלייה,
Vekabeil mikalyeh, it wants to burn down this pile of grain. ואידבנא
בקיטמיה, Ve'isba bekitmeh, and roll itself in the ashes. Have you ever
seen like, you know, the elephants that they go in the mud
in order to deal with like, you know, you know, their as-
the-
the bite, the heat? Well also the bites, right? Isn't it insect
bite? Maybe to get the insects off of them. I don't know.
Anyway, so this ox wants to roll around in ashes, and it's
very smart and it realizes how to make ashes. You take a
fire, you light a pile of grain. Okay. So that's why, but
we're talking that yes, you wanted the ashes and that's why it's
חילול שבת Chilul Shabbos and there could be a case of an
ox just like that. So the גמרא Gemara says ומנא ידעינן, Uminah
yedinan, how would you know that that would be the reality of
why the ox burnt it down? דלבתר דקלייה, Dilebasar d'kalyei, because after
it burned down this pile of grain, we see קמיטנפא בקיטמיה, Kamisba
bekitmeh, we see it rolling around in the ashes. So you can
figure out its intention. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says fine. ומי
שכיחא האי גוונא, Umichika hai gavna, really? Does anything like that ever
happen? Is there an animal that smart that knows how to do
that? אין, In, yes. דההוא תורא דהוי בי רב פפא, Dehahu tora
dehavai bei Rav Papa, there was an ox in the house of
רב פפא. Rav Papa. דהוה כאיב ליה שיניה, Dehavai kiven lei shichnei,
that its gums were bothering it. Okay. עייל פדקא לניזא, Ayeil pitka
lenizaisa, it uncovered a barrel of like of of mead or
some type of you know drink.
ושתי שיכרא, Veshati shichra, and it drank and it drank the beer,
drank the mead, ואינצי, Ve'itzi, and that helped its gums. So you
have sometimes very smart animals. Okay. Anyway, even though the simple sense
of our משנה Mishnah is you're burning it down to be totally
destructive, and that's considered חילול שבת, Chilul Shabbos, the גמרא Gemara says
לא, lo, no, it could be a case that you're burning it
down for the purpose of the ashes. It's not totally destructive. And
only when you're doing it to serve some purpose would it not
be would it be considered חילול שבת.
Chilul Shabbos. Michshama d'mishtab- it must have been totally urbanized. You think-
in other words, a farmer you would think would like the discussion
would be like this is what animals always do, this is what
animals don't do.
I don't know what to tell you, maybe. Okay. אמר אביי אמר
רבא קמיה דרב פפא. Amar Abaye amar Raba kamin d'Rav Papa. Now
the rabbi said to רב פפא: Rav Papa: מי
מצית אמרת, Mi matsis amras, how can you say that שור דומיא
דידיה, Shor dumya dideh, that we're talking that the ox is like
you, that the- and therefore they both you know the same way
you wanted to get the ashes that's what we would say the
scenario is the ox wanted to get the ashes. והקתני, Veha katani,
but let's look at the other part of the
משנה. Mishnah. Well, שור דומיא דידיה והקתני, Shor dumya dideh veha katani,
the first part of the משנה Mishnah said: שור שבייש פטור, Shor
shebiyesh patur, if an ox caused embarrassment you're exempt. ואדם שבייש חייב,
Vehu shebiyesh chayav, if you cause embarrassment you're חייב. chayav. Now, שור
דומיא דידיה, Shor dumya dideh, if we say that the scenario is
the same, the type of similar type of intention is being referred
to in the משנה. Mishnah. So how could that be by the
case of embarrassment?
נתכוין לבייש היכי משכחת לה, Niskavein levayesh heichi mishkachas lo, your only-
remember, you're only חייב chayav for paying for בושת boshes if you
intentionally are doing are trying to cause embarrassment. So what would be
a case that an ox wants to do something to embarrass the
person that it's goring? Right? So clearly we're not talking about that
the animal has the same intentionality as the person being described. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, actually, you can have it. כגון דנתכוין
להזיק, Kegon deniskavein lehazik, it's true, you don't have an ox trying
to embarrass somebody. But you do have an ox trying to inflict
damage, and if you- and that's sufficient intention for a human being
to be חייב chayav on embarrassment. דאמר מר: De'amar mar: נתכוין להזיק
אע"פ שלא נתכוין לבייש, niskavein lehazik af al pi shelo niskavein levayesh,
that you are liable for paying בושת boshes if you intentionally inflicted
damage even if you weren't trying to bring about embarrassment. So we
actually can have, that actually is easier than the ashes case. Okay.
You and the ox are both trying to inflict damage. If you
did it you pay for בושת boshes because intention to inflict damage
is enough intention to pay for בושת. boshes. But if your ox
tried to inflict damage, it does not pay for בושת. boshes. That
actually is an easy case. And yes, the משנה Mishnah can be
talking about the same intention that the ox has and that the
human has. Okay. רבא אמר, Rava amar, so anyway, we've now explained
that it could be by שבת Shabbos you need to have intention
to create the ashes, some type of intention to do something constructive,
and that would be the scenario we're talking about. And that's why
it would be קים ליה. kimlei. רבא אמר מתניתין בשוגג. Rava amar
matnisin b'shogeg. Our משנה Mishnah is not talking about intentional, our משנה
Mishnah is talking about unintentional, or שוגג shogeg meaning
that you are not willingly violating שבת. Shabbos. Now it is important
to know that a classic case of שוגג shogeg on שבת Shabbos
is either you forgot that it was שבת Shabbos or you did
not know that it was forbidden. But you were not a willful
violator.
And
this gets to the question Michael asked. Do you say קם ליה
kim lei even if somebody did an עבירה aveira without being intentional
about it, without being willful about it? וכדתנא v'chiditana like we talked
in the דבי חזקיה, Bei Chizkiyahu, like the דבי חזקיה Bei Chizkiyahu
teaches, famous teaching of דבי חזקיה Bei Chizkiyahu about the parameters of
קם ליה. kim lei. דתנא דבי חזקיה, d'tana d'bei Chizkiyahu, דבי חזקיה
Bei Chizkiyahu taught, מכה אדם ומכה בהמה. makeh adam u'makeh behemah. It
says מכה אדם יומת, makeh adam yumos, it says מכה בהמה ישלמנה
makeh behemah yeshalmena ומכה אדם יומת. u'makeh adam yumos. If you smite
an animal you pay for it, and if you kill a human
being you are put to death. So מה מכה בהמה לא חלקת,
mah makeh behemah lo chalakta, the same way if you smite an
animal you pay for it, now remember אדם מועד לעולם. adam muad
l'olam. So if a human being kills an animal he pays for
it regardless of circumstances. לא
חלקת, lo chalakta, you don't make
distinctions בו bo בין שוגג ובין מזיד, bein shogeg u'bein meizid, whether
it was willful or
unintentional or willful. בין מתכוין לשאינו מתכוין, bein miskaven l'she'eino miskaven, intentional
or not intentional. בין דרך ירידה לדרך עלייה, bein derech yerida l'derech
aliya, whether he was on a downward movement or an upward movement,
that is based on גלות, galus, because when you are גלות galus
the chopping of the wood and the top of the axe flying
off, the גמרא Gemara understands that it is only when you are
moving your axe downward and the top of it flies off, you
get גלות. galus. But if you are moving your axe upward and
it flies off, you don't. So those are distinctions that matter in
cases for גלות. galus. These issues of שוגג shogeg and מזיד, meizid,
these might matter in cases of whether you have done an act
of murder, an act of חייב גלות. chayav galus. But when it
comes to killing an animal and paying, none of this matters. אדם
מועד לעולם, adam muad l'olam, you pay under all circumstances. In all
those cases when you have killed an animal, לפוטרו ממון, l'potro mamon,
we make no distinctions in any of those scenarios to exempt you,
אלא לחייבו ממון. ela l'chayvo mamon. We say in all those cases
you pay for killing an animal. So the same way that's true
that you always pay regardless by killing an animal, אף מכה אדם,
af makeh adam, so it is מכה בהמה ישלמנה, makeh behemah yeshalmena,
when you kill an animal you pay for it regardless of circumstance,
and מכה אדם יומת, makeh adam yumos, when you kill a human
being you are put to death. Now not you are put to
death regardless of circumstances, you need to have obviously been intentional, it
has to be an act of murder. But we're reading it when
you kill a human being, you never pay for damages.
The only thing that can be done to you is put to
death. It will be never any payment for damages when you kill
a human regardless of circumstances. אף מכה אדם לא תחלק, af makeh
adam lo tachlok, don't make any distinctions בו bo בין שוגג למזיד,
bein shogeg l'meizid, בין מתכוין לשאינו מתכוין, bein miskaven l'she'eino miskaven, whether
it was
unintentional or intentional, willful, not willful, בין דרך ירידה לדרך עלייה, bein
derech yerida l'derech aliya, going up, going down. Don't make any of
those distinctions to say, oh in this case we're going to make
you pay money. No, אלא לפוטרו ממון, ela l'potro mamon, by when
a human, when a life is taken or any capital crime is
committed, it is how we're going to read it, like חילול שבת,
chilul Shabbos, you're always going to be exempt. So the principle of
קם ליה, kim lei, and this is very important, because there are
two ideas about קם ליה. kim lei. One idea of קם ליה
kim lei is basically that it is learned from the פסוק pasuk
of כדי רשעתו, k'dei rishaso, because based on your wickedness you are
punished. And the גמרא Gemara says רשעה אחת אתה מחייבו, rishas achas
atta m'chaivo, you make somebody pay for one wicked act, not for
two wicked acts. Which basically means that if בית דין Beis Din
is inflicting a punishment, they're only going to inflict one punishment, not
multiple punishments. That's a type of a thing we say that if
for example you do an act that is deserving of מלקות malkus
and deserving of ממון, mamon, that you're only going to get the
מלקות, malkus, you're not going to pay. And that is only when
בית דין Beis Din actually inflicts the punishment. That's a type of
a קם ליה kim lei where it is because we are inflicting
one punishment we're not going to impose another one. And we have
to actively impose the punishment. That would be a case of like
מלקות malkus and ממון, mamon, lashes and money. But when it comes
to a case of a capital crime, that's a קם ליה kim
lei of a different category. Even if we're not going to impose
any punishment. This person did it accidentally, בשוגג, b'shogeg, אינו מתכוין, eino
miskaven, all these things that there would be no basis, he was
מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos but it was a complete accident. It doesn't
matter. The weight of the act that it was a capital crime,
even though it was not a scenario where בית דין Beis Din
could ever punish the person, the weight of the act of a
capital crime erases any monetary payment that could be made.
So that clear meaning it's a very different idea of קם ליה.
kim lei. One idea is we're not going to impose two punishments.
What חזקיה's Chizkiyahu saying is when it comes to an act that's
a capital crime, it has nothing to do with whether we're imposing
the punishment or not. The fact that you've done a capital crime
is so weighty that there will never be any payment of money.
So in those cases we will never say לחייבו ממון l'chaivo mamon
אלא לפוטרו ממון. ela l'potro mamon. Case so therefore, if somebody is
מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, even בשוגג beshogeg they're not going to pay
the monetary payment. So אמרי רבנן לרבא, amrei rabanan le'Rava, so the
Rabbis said to רבא, Rava, מי מצית מוקמת לה בשוגג? mi matzis
mukamt lah beshogeg? How can you say our Mishnah says that you're
exempt from payment even if you did it בשוגג, beshogeg, you burnt
down this wheat stack? והא מפני שניתן מנפשו קתני. veha mipnei shenitan
mnafsho katani. The Mishnah says
you're liable the death penalty. And you said if it's בשוגג beshogeg
you're not liable the death penalty? So רבא Rava says no, הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's
what the Mishnah means.
כיון דבמזיד ניתן מנפשו, keivan debemezid nitan mnafsho, since were you to
do it intentionally, you'd be deserving of the death penalty, והיכי דמי,
ve'heichi dami, what would be that scenario? דקבעי לאפרה, dekaba'i le'afrah, that
you want the ashes. Remember this is getting back to that issue.
Since there are cases of burning down the wheat stack that you're
חייב, chayav, that you're חייב
מיתה, chayav misah, that you would get the death penalty, which is
what you did it intentionally and you did it for the sake
of the ashes. So since there are some scenarios of burning it
down that you would actually get the death penalty, השתא בשוגג פטור,
hashta beshogeg patur, even though that's not true in this scenario, this
scenario was unintentional, nevertheless it's enough of an act of חילול שבת
chilul Shabbos that you do not pay. So ניתן מנפשו nitan mnafsho
does not mean right now you're deserving the death penalty, it means
the nature of the act is one that it could bring about
the death penalty under other circumstances. And therefore that is enough to
exempt you. So we have a very important principle that we say
קים ליה kimlei when it's something that is liable the death penalty,
it's a capital crime even if we're not imposing it, even if
it's בשוגג. beshogeg. Okay that's a very important principle about קים ליה.
kimlei. Now how did this address the question we asked about שבת,
Shabbos, about צריך לאפרה? tzarich le'afrah? What's the still scenario? How do
you address the case in the Mishnah? Is the guy understood to
be burning down the wheat stack for the sake of the ashes?
So רש"י Rashi says no, once the גמרא Gemara is saying intent
doesn't matter, you say קים ליה kimlei regardless of intent, that would
be true even if your intent was to not, not for the
sake of the ashes. Right that seems to be the point of
רבא's Rava answer, right? רבא's Rava answer seems to be look, you
don't need intent to say קים ליה. kimlei. Even בשוגג beshogeg you
would say קים ליה. kimlei. Remember what was the גמרא's Gemara question?
The גמרא's Gemara question was where is the guy doing it for
the sake of the ashes in the Mishnah? And רבא's Rava answer
seems to be well you don't need intent because we're talking about
you say קים ליה kimlei even בשוגג. beshogeg. Everybody with me? Yes?
Okay. תוספות Tosafot says wait one minute. There's a huge difference.
If I, if I, in one case I am not willingly violating
שבת. Shabbos. I think that it is Sunday, or I don't think
it's אסור assur to do this on שבת. Shabbos. But the act
that I am doing is an act of חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos.
I am burning down the wheat stack for the sake of the
ashes. That's defined as an act of חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. So
then you could tell me it doesn't matter if I'm willingly breaking
שבת Shabbos or not, you say קים ליה. kimlei. But if I
am burning down the wheat stack for purely destructive motives, not for
the sake of the ashes, then that's not an act of חילול
שבת chilul Shabbos at all, right? So he says what does the,
what does רבא's Rava answer mean? Wonderful. רבא Rava said we're talking
even בשוגג. beshogeg. But to say even בשוגג, beshogeg, even בשוגג beshogeg
means you're not a willful violator. But wouldn't you still need the
intent to define it as an act of חילול שבת? chilul Shabbos?
If you're missing that intent, right, then presumably, just because physically the
act could be חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos, but isn't intent constituent of
defining it as an act of חילול שבת? chilul Shabbos? Not intent
to violate, intent to want something constructive out of the act, intent
to want the ashes out of the act. Okay? So תוספות Tosafot
says actually you still do need that intent, that according to רבא,
Rava, all רבא Rava is saying is that you don't need to
be a willful violator, but רבא Rava is not disagreeing with the
fact that you would still need intent to do something constructive. So
that raises an interesting question of what is the extent of חזקיה's
Chizkiya teaching? חזקיה Chizkiya says you don't need to actually be deserving
of the death penalty, you just need to have done the act.
Okay, even if you did not willfully do it and you're not
deserving of a death penalty. What if I didn't have the intent
that normally is defined as part of what makes the act the
sin? Right? Would you still say קים ליה kimlei in that case?
So רש"י Rashi says yeah because physically it's an act of חילול
שבת, chilul Shabbos, with the right intent it would have been an
act of חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. And תוספות Tosafot says no in
that case it's just not חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. Because here intent
it defines the nature of the act. Yes, no.
Yeah professor Shorchman, you want to say something? Exactly as you're saying,
that would mean according to תוספות, Tosafot, for example, all the people
out there who are oblivious of שבת Shabbos in all ways.
No, that would, no, oblivious still means they didn't, they were not
willfully violating. But in terms of how they defined what type of
an act they did, right, that's תוספות's Tosafot point. חזקיה Chizkiya will
tell you you don't need any awareness that is relevant for let's
say culpability, any awareness that is relevant for what it means to
be a willing violator. Okay, but you still... you need the intent
that is necessary to define the nature of the act. Okay, I'll
give you another extreme case. Let's say you had a case about
מתעסק. misyasek. Let's say you had a case
that I was, well right, or that I was completely unaware that
like, you know, I was right, I don't know,
you know, I'm trying to think of a case. I was, I
was just gesticulating and my hand like turned on a light switch
or something like that and the light switch is also connected to
you know, and then it started a fire, whatever. You know, as
I was gesticulating my hand knocked down a torch that started a
fire that burnt something. What would you say? Oh, קמלי Kimlei because
I also was מחלל שבת? mechalel Shabbos? Or would you say no,
that's not a case of not willingly violating, that I didn't even...
it's a completely... there intent... lack of intent means that I didn't
even do the act. Okay. So I think like that's the question
of how much, at what stage would you say the lack of
intent means that you didn't even, you weren't even מחלל שבת, mechalel
Shabbos, not that you were מחלל בשוגג. mechalel beshogeg. Right.
Do you find it striking at all that the language of קמלי
Kimlei does not appear anywhere in this סוגיא? Sugya?
Well right, so that could be because of the point that I
said, that the קמלי Kimlei is more specifically, oh we have to
see, you're right, like how that word is used. But a classic,
more classic use of קמלי Kimlei is when the punishment is imposed.
Here, the fact that the חילול שבת chillul Shabbos is so weighty
that it outweighs even if there's no punishment, it outweighs anything, it
could be a principle that's broader than קמלי, Kimlei, correct.
And then I don't remember, could you remind me, like my ox
gores somebody? I don't have to pay hospital bills, I don't have
to pay workers' comp?
No, you don't pay hospital, you don't pay workers, you just pay...
that's because... that's a דרשה drasha from a פסוק? pasuk?
Yeah, we learned that איש כי יתן מום בעמיתו, Ish ki yiten
mum ba'amito, like איש בעמיתו ולא שור בעמיתו Ish ba'amito velo shor
ba'amito is the דרשה. drasha. Yeah. Okay, Johnny, you had a question?
I think the distinction what Dov was talking about, they do distinction
between מזיד, Mezid, שוגג, Shogeg, and מתכוין, Miskaven, אינו מתכוין. Eino Miskaven.
Right.
You mean so what's the difference between שוגג, Shogeg, מזיד, Mezid, מתכוין,
Miskaven, אינו מתכוין? Eino Miskaven? Right, right.
Exactly what you're, what you're explaining.
Right, right. So now I do want to say one last thing
I'll say about this and then we'll do the next משנה Mishna
is that תוספות Tosafos actually says why did you need to say
the difference between שוגג, Shogeg, מזיד, Mezid, מתכוין, Miskaven, אינו מתכוין? Eino
Miskaven? תוספות Tosafos actually says, and this is a point that תוספות
Tosafos said a few times in this מסכת, Masechet, that the difference
between שוגג Shogeg and מזיד Mezid is the sort of classic case
about I did an act that's חייב מיתה chayav misa and I
did another act at the same time that would be a תשלומין
tashlumin act. Like I burnt down the haystack while, you know, which
is both חילול שבת chillul Shabbos and a נזק. nezek. Or somebody,
you know, shot somebody and they killed the person and they also
ruined the suit with the guy's blood. Okay, that would be a
case of, of that one case. מתכוין, Miskaven, אינו מתכוין Eino Miskaven
תוספות Tosafos says also comes to exempt you from something else, which
comes to exempt you from civil payment due to loss of life.
Meaning that's a different concept. Somebody kills somebody unintentionally, okay, forget קמלי,
Kimlei, you don't have to pay for other types of liability. Maybe
since in that case we can't, like the OJ case, if we
can't prosecute the guy criminally, maybe at least we can make him
pay civilly for loss of life. Okay, and that תוספות Tosafos says
is also what חזקיה Chizkiya is saying. Is you'll never be any
payment for some other liability that's incurred during that time and there
also will never be any payment due to loss of life either.
Okay, you can never pay for loss of life. The only thing
you can do for loss of life is get prosecuted for murder,
you can't get prosecuted civilly. Alright, so that's also what תוספות Tosafos
does a little bit with those phrases. Let's take a look now
at the next משנה. Mishna. שור שהיה רודף. Shor shehayah rodeif. These
are now fun. Like now that we've gone, you know, we did
one case about parsing the case of the Torah splitting the animal.
Is it יושם השור, yusham hashor, יוכל השור? yukhal hashor? Now we
did a little bit of קמלי. Kimlei. Now we're going to do
a little bit of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraya.
Okay. So שור שהיה
רודף אחר שור אחר, Shor shehayah rodeif acher shor acher, one ox
was running after another ox to gore it.
והוזק, Vehuzak, and then the owners ran after it and found one
ox on the ground like totally, you know, bleeding. וזה אומר שורך
הזיק. Vezeh omeir shorkha heizeik. So one guy says your ox just
gored my ox. וזה אומר לא כי על סלע לקה. Vezeh omeir
lo ki al sela lakah. No,
it tripped over a rock, it wasn't my ox. So המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. So the one who comes to
get paid, he has the burden of proof. Now the question is
going to be what constitutes sufficient burden of proof? Do you need
two direct witnesses? Let's say the other ox had blood on its
horns. You know what I'm saying? Like or you know, let's say
this ox had clear horn holes in it, in its body, right?
At what stage is it considered a burden of proof? But the
point is, certainly the point here is that circumstantial evidence under many
cases, maybe all cases, is not enough. You want to prove it,
it's not enough that it looks like it. Okay. היו שנים רודפין
אחר אחד. hayu shenayim rodfin acher echad. Now Reuven and Shimon's oxen
were running after, one ox owned by Reuven, one ox owned by
Shimon, they were both running after Levi's ox. וזה אומר שורך הזיק.
Vezeh omeir shorkha heizeik. Somehow it was clear that one of the
oxen gored. Maybe a witness at a distance saw an ox gore,
but didn't see which ox gored. So Reuven says to Shimon, it
was your ox. וזה אומר שורך הזיק. Vezeh omeir shorkha heizeik. And
Shimon says to Reuven, no, it was your ox. שניהם פטורין. sheneihem
paturin. They're both exempt because each one... Levi can't prove from either
which, which one of them owes him money. They each say the
other guy's ox did it. Okay, it's another version of המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. אם היו
שניהם של איש אחד. Im hayu shneihem shel ish echad. Now, let's
say Reuven owned both oxen. Okay, then שניהם חייבים. shneihem chayavim. Then
both oxen are חייב, chayav, which is a little funny way of
saying it, but if Reuven owned both oxen and Shimon doesn't know
which ox gored, nevertheless he knows that one of Reuven's oxen gored,
so at least he can collect money from Reuven. Now, this is
a little bit of interest because if it's a שור תם shor
tam and we פוסקין pasken like Rabbi Akiva, if we פוסקין pasken
that's just a debt with a lien on the ox, then you
could say, I don't care which of your oxen did it, you
owe me $50 or $100. But if it's a יחלוט השור yuchlat
hashor like Rabbi Akiva, I may know that I own one of
your oxen but I can't prove which ox I own, because right,
the fact that your ox gored means I become now an owner
in your ox. So let's say I know that I own one
of your oxen but I can't prove which one. But presumably there's
some recourse there, right? I know you have property of mine, even
if I can't exactly prove which of those oxen are mine, I
know one of them is, so it's still I can still prove
though that you have property of mine, so presumably I can somehow
get some satisfaction there.
Yes, just structurally, if we're trying to keep the principle of המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav haraya, the way it's structured here
is Reuven and Shimon's oxen and it gores Levi's ox. Right. Wouldn't
the correct teaching be for Levi to say to Reuven, your ox
gored mine, you owe me money, and he says it wasn't my
ox, it was his ox?
Meaning why do they say שורך הזיק shurcha heezik rather than שורו
הזיק? shoro heezik? Yeah, it's true. Right, I understand. Why do they
have Reuven and Shimon talking to one another? Reuven and Shimon should
both be talking to Levi. Yeah, I do understand that, but yeah,
it's true. It would be a little bit more direct to frame
it that way, but I was wondering the same thing. Okay. אם
היו שניהם של. Im hayu shneihem shel. Okay, now. אם היה אחד
גדול ואחד קטן. Im haya echad gadol ve-echad katan. Both oxen are
owned by Reuven, but one's a big ox and one's a small
ox, and they're both תם. tam. So remember, if the small ox
gored, the ניזק neezak is going to be out money, he's not
going to get full satisfaction from the value of the small ox.
Okay. הניזק אומר גדול הזיק. Ha-neezak omer gadol heezik.
So the ניזק neezak says the big one gored and I'm going
to be able to get my at least full half payment out
of the big one. והמזיק אומר לא כי אלא קטן הזיק. Ve-ha-mazik
omer lo ki ela katan heezik. No, the small little one gored
you, gored your animal, and therefore you'll take the small one, but
you're not going to get your full payment, full half payment. אחד
תם ואחד מועד. Echad tam ve-echad muad.
Let's say one of Reuven's oxen was a תם tam and one
was a מועד. muad. הניזק אומר מועד הזיק. Ha-neezak omer muad heezik.
The ניזק neezak says the מועד muad gored and therefore I'm going
to get full payment. והמזיק אומר לא כי אלא תם הזיק. Ve-ha-mazik
omer lo ki ela tam heezik. No, the תם tam gored and
you're only going to get half payment. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi
mechavero alav haraya. So Shimon has the burden of proof, okay, and
he's not going to get full satisfaction. היו הניזוקין שנים. Hayu ha-neezukin
shnayim. Now, let's say the damaged, there were two oxen that were
damaged. אחד גדול
ואחד קטן. Echad gadol ve-echad katan. והמזיקין שנים. Ve-ha-mazikin shnayim. And there
were two oxen that were involved in the goring. אחד גדול ואחד
קטן. Echad gadol ve-echad katan. One big one and small. So הניזק
אומר, Ha-neezak omer, the one who suffered the damage says, and they
both belong, both damaged oxen belong to Shimon and both damaging goring
oxen belong to Reuven. הניזק אומר גדול הזיק את הגדול וקטן הזיק
את הקטן. Ha-neezak omer gadol heezik et ha-gadol ve-katan heezik et ha-katan.
And let's say presumably they were both תם. tam. So הניזק neezak
says, so Shimon said, the big one gored the big one, so
where I suffered the biggest loss, the goring of the big one,
I'll be able to get paid in at least get my full
half payment because it came out of your big
ox. וקטן הזיק את הקטן. Ve-katan heezik et ha-katan. והמזיק אומר לא
כי. Ve-ha-mazik omer lo ki. Nope, that's not what happened. אלא קטן
את הגדול. Ela katan et ha-gadol. The
small one gored your big ox, so you're not going to get
your full big half payment from the big ox because you're only
going to get it out of my small little one. וגדול את
הקטן. Ve-gadol et ha-katan. And the big one gored the small one,
so you'll get your full half payment for the small one, but
not for the big one. Or אחד תם ואחד מועד. Echad tam
ve-echad muad. One of the goring oxen was a תם tam and
one was a מועד. muad. הניזק אומר מועד הזיק את הגדול. Ha-neezak
omer muad heezik et ha-gadol. The מועד muad gored the big one,
so I'll get my full payment for the big loss. ותם את
הקטן. Ve-tam et ha-katan. And the half payment I'll get, you know,
for the small loss, the תם tam gored the small one. והמזיק
אומר לא כי. Ve-ha-mazik omer lo ki. No, it was the opposite.
אלא תם את הגדול. Ela tam et ha-gadol. The תם tam gored
the big one, so that big payment you're only going to get
half. ומועד את הקטן. Ve-muad et ha-katan. And the מועד muad gored
the small one, so the full payment will only be for the
small one. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. So the
principle of all these is המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav
haraya. Very good. Okay. אמר רבי Amar Rabbi let's see the גמרא.
Gemara. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא זאת אומרת. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba zot omeret. This משנה Mishnah tells you that it says that
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav haraya, חולקים עליו חבריו על
סומכוס. cholkim alav chaverav al Sumchos. That there's that Sumchos' colleagues disagree
with him.
דאמר de-amar ממון המוטל בספק חולקים. mamon hamutal be-safek cholkim. Sumchos says
whenever there's a doubt about who owes money, you split it. Now,
it doesn't mean whenever there's a doubt, right? Let's say I go
over to David and I say David, that nice Maserati you have,
that's mine. And you say, what are you talking about? המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. I say what's okay, I פוסקין
pasken like Sumchos, let's take half. Okay, so it's not anytime there's
a doubt, there has to be some objective basis. There has to
be
some... This case, clearly, everybody's looking at it, sees something happened, one
of these animals gored, you just don't know which one. So any
normal observer would say there's an objective ספק safek here whether it
was the תם tam or the מועד, muad, the big or the
small. So סומכוס Sumchos would say if that's true, the circumstances basically
speak to the idea that there's a question what happened, we ignore
the claims and the counterclaims and we ignore המוציא מחברו Hamotzi Mechavero
and we just say there's no way we're going to resolve this,
split it. That's what סומכוס Sumchos says. And this משנה Mishna teaches
you you don't split it, even in a case of objective doubt,
you say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya.
Exact same משנה Mishna comes up, the first משנה Mishna בבא מציעא.
Bava Metzia.
Yeah, a lot of this is discussed elsewhere, בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
certainly. Okay. אמר ליה רב אבא בר ממל לרבי חייא בר אבא,
Amar Lei Rav Abba Bar Mammal L'Rabbi Chiyya Bar Abba, אמר סומכוס
אפילו ברי וברי? Amar Sumchos Afilu Bari V'Bari? Would סומכוס Sumchos say
you split it even if both want to say you definitely owe
me money, no I definitely don't owe you money? Meaning, maybe when
סומכוס Sumchos says you split, it's when each of the litigants say
"I don't know what happened, I don't know what happened". In that
case, we'll say split it. But if the ניזק nizak is saying...
if the מזיק, mazik, the one who you're trying to get the
money from is saying "I definitely do not owe you money", maybe
in that case סומכוס Sumchos would respect the idea of the, you
know, of the מוחזק, muchzak, and he would say המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya. If he's making a claim that he
definitely does not owe the money, maybe we don't say חולקין, cholkin,
maybe we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya. So
he says, would סומכוס Sumchos say even by ברי וברי bari v'bari
that you would split it? אמר אין, Amar In, yes, אמר סומכוס
אפילו ברי וברי. Amar Sumchos Afilu Bari V'Bari. Even if the guy
is saying "I definitely don't owe you money", nevertheless סומכוס Sumchos says
you split it. וממאי דמתניתין בברי וברי הוא? U'mimai de'matnitin b'bari v'bari
hu? Now, the fact that you asked it means that you understood
because we were saying our משנה mishna is an anti-סומכוס משנה. Sumchos
mishna. So and we're saying that that shows that there's a debate
even in a case of ברי וברי. bari v'bari.
How do you know that our משנה mishna is a case of
ברי וברי bari v'bari just to say that that position shows a
non-סומכוס Sumchos position? וממאי דמתניתין בברי וברי U'mimai de'matnitin b'bari v'bari הוא?
hu? דקתני
זה אומר שורך הזיק, D'ktani Zeh Omer Shorchecha Hezik, this one says
your ox gored, וזה אומר לא כי, v'zeh omer lo ki, no,
that's not, it's the opposite. Meaning it doesn't sound like they're saying
maybe your ox. When he says no, rather it was your, you
know, the other one ox, it sounds like everybody is making a
definite claim. Now, so rather than saying that סומכוס Sumchos agrees in
that case המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya, we're saying
that even though everybody's making a definite claim, סומכוס Sumchos would say
you split it and the משנה mishna is in a position that
disagrees with סומכוס. Sumchos. Okay. מתקיף לה רב פפא, Matkif Lah Rav
Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa asked on this. מדרישא ברי וברי
סיפא נמי ברי וברי. Mi'de'reisha bari v'bari seifa nami bari v'bari. Okay,
if our משנה mishna is talking that everybody is making a definite
claim, that's the beginning, it's also the end. Let's look at the
end case of the משנה. mishna. אימא סיפא. Eima seifa. Let's look
at the end case. היה אחד גדול ואחד קטן, Hayah echad gadol
v'echad katan, one was big, one was small. ניזק אומר גדול הזיק
ומזיק אומר לא כי אלא קטן הזיק. Nizak omer gadol hezik u'mazik
omer lo ki ela katan hezik. The ניזק nizak says the big
one gored and I'll get my full half-payment from the big one,
they're both תם, tam, and the מזיק mazik says no, only the
small one gored. אחד תם ואחד מועד, Echad tam v'echad muad, or
one was תם tam and one was מועד. muad. ניזק אומר מועד
הזיק. Nizak omer muad hezik. The מועד muad did and I'll get
full damages. ומזיק אומר לא כי אלא תם הזיק. U'mazik omer lo
ki ela tam hezik. No, you're only going to have half damages.
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya.
Fine, that's the משנה mishna and everybody's making a ברי bari claim.
So הא ומאי דאי, Ha u'mai de'i, what's the implication of the
משנה? mishna? The implication of the משנה mishna is that if the
ניזק nizak cannot prove his bigger claim, so שקיל כדאמר מזיק. shakil
k'de'amar mazik. He would have to... he would at least get what
the מזיק mazik claimed. Like the ניזק nizak made a big claim,
the מזיק mazik made a small claim, it says the ניזק's nizak
got to prove his point. If the ניזק nizak doesn't prove his
point, presumably at least he's entitled to collect based on what the
מזיק mazik said, right? But one minute. נימא תהוי תיובתא דרבא בר
נתן, Nima tehei tiyuvta d'Rabba bar Natan, let's say that's a challenge
on רבא בר נתן. Rabba bar Natan. דאמר טענו חטין והודה לו
בשעורין פטור. D'amar ta'ano chittin v'hoda lo b'se'orin patur. Okay, I go
and I say, David, David, you owe me a pound of
wheat, I gave you a pound of wheat to watch for me.
And he says, no you didn't, you only gave me a pound
of barley. Okay, so we'd say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi Mechavero
Alav Haraya, I can't prove it. Now, do I say well, at
least give me the pound of barley? You at least admitted to
a pound of barley. Okay, or do we say no, the fact
that I said a pound of wheat meant that I was implicitly
saying you don't owe me barley, you only owe me wheat. So
even though you've admitted to barley, maybe you don't have to give
it to me. I never asked for barley, I implicitly was saying
you don't owe me barley, you only owe me wheat. So that's
what we say. If I demand wheat and you concede barley, you
don't have to pay me anything. Okay, now that's true because my
claim of wheat was a ברי bari claim. I didn't go and
say maybe you owe me wheat, maybe you owe me barley. I
said you owe me wheat, which means only wheat. So if it's
a ברי bari claim, it excludes the other claim. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying, say the same thing here, right? The ניזק nizak
says the big one damaged. Okay, which is implicitly saying the small
one did not damage. No, no... Not the small one, only the
big one, that's the one that damaged. So when you concede the
small one, why do you have to pay anything? I've implicitly rejected
your claim about the small one. If I'm making a ברי bari
claim, then I am saying the small one did not damage me,
only the big one. Okay, Jonathan, you've got a look on your
face. Because if it's a different, here's why it's different. If it's
about מועד muad or something of that nature, you're right. I say
you owe me two hundred dollars and you say only one hundred.
Okay, so two hundred dollars includes a demand of one hundred dollars.
But if we're talking about a תם, tam, then maybe it's not
the same. I say I own that animal, that animal gored and
I own half of that animal, and you say no, the small
animal gored and you only own half of the other animal. So,
but I agree, if it's all about, if it's about the circumstances
but ultimately it's a demand for cash, then it's not the same.
But if it's about תם, tam, it is more similar, right? So
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, if you're going to tell me
the משנה Mishnah is ברי bari and ברי, bari, why do I
get to collect based on at least your, what you conceded? I
made a ברי bari claim that rejected what you were conceding. So
it should be like I asked for wheat, you said barley, I
don't get anything. So okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question. So
what we will do is we will end here and we will
pick up tomorrow with trying to figure out whether our משנה Mishnah
is talking about ברי bari and ברי bari or ברי bari and
שמא. shema.
I say שעורים, se'orim, then technically...